Guide to the Winterhouse Art and Design Collection of Type Specimens
Yale University Arts Library
Winterhouse Art and Design collection of type specimens
1971-2008
1996-2004
ART 22
Yale University Arts Library
2.17
(4 boxes)
The collection comprises type specimens collected by William Drenttel and Jessica Helfand in the course of their work as principals of Winterhouse Design and later Winterhouse Institute.
Drenttel, William, 1953-2013
Helfand, Jessica, 1960-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of William Drenttel and Jessica Helfand, 2013.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Winterhouse was a design consultancy founded by partners William Drenttel and Jessica Helfand. According to their website, "Winterhouse Studio focuse[d] on editorial development and online media; cultural and educational institutions; and social innovation initiatives... Winterhouse Institute focuse[d] on non-profit, self-initiated projects that support design education as well as social and political initiatives."
Scope and Contents
The collection comprises type specimens collected by William Drenttel and Jessica Helfand in the course of their work as principals of Winterhouse Design and later Winterhouse Institute.
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically by manufacturer/publisher and then chronologically by date of publication.
Design; Type specimens (documents)
- Original Accession, 1991-2004
  Scope and Contents
  Accession dated August 15, 2013.
  - A. Colish, Inc.
    - Types Available, undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Adobe
    - Adobe Type Library, 1994; 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Digital Type Foundry
    - [T-26: this is the Twentieth Supplement], undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Emigre
    - Emigre Font Book, 1992; 1 (Box 2)
    - Emigre Font Book 2, 1993; 1 (Box 3)
    - Emigre Fonts: the stuff that words are made of, 1995; 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1996 Emigre Catalog, 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Mrs. Eaves, 1996; 2 copies (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - More Mrs. Eaves, 1996; 2 copies (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Hypnopaedia: 140 patterns, 1997; 4 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Three copies, including one with a dust jacket, and one poster.
    - Emigre presents the typography of Elliott Peter Earls at the Apollo Program, 1998; 1 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - The Emigre Product Catalog, 1998; 1 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - The Emigre fonts Library, 1999 2000; 3 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Includes two copies of the 1999 edition.
    - The Emigre Product Catalog, 2000; 1 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Dalliance: a new font design by Frank Heine…, 2001; 2 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - The Emigre Catalog, magazines typefaces, music, books, and more, 2001 2002; 2 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Émigré Magazine #60, 61, 2001 2002; 2 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Émigré Magazine #62, 63, 2002; 2 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Emigre Type Specimen series Booklet 1-4, 2001 2002; 8 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - The Emigre Catalog 1984-2002, 2 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Introducing "Tribute" a family of 8 fonts by Frank Heine…, 2003; 1 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Typographic Taste Makers, 2003; 2 copies (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Poppi, 2004; 1 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Various Types, 2004; 1 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Emigre fonts typeface designs by..., undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Font Bureau
    - Type Specimens, 1995; 1 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Type Specimens 2nd edition, 1997; 1 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Font Bureau Retail 24, 2000; 1 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Font Bureau 1-Line Showings, 2001; 1 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Font Bureau 1-Line Specimens, second edition., 2003; 1 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - FontHaus Inc.
    - FontHaus Catalog 10, 1999; 1 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Fontshop International
    - Style Finder, 1993; 1 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Typographic Resources, 1998; 1 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - AnyFontFont. Anytime. Anywhere., 2000; 1 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Fontastic Selection, 2000; 1 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - FontFont Catalogue 2000, 1 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Virus Fonts by Jonathan Barnbrook, 2000; 1 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - FontFont Library, 1/95, undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Hoefler & Frere-Jones Typography
    - New Typefaces, 2004; 2 copies (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - [Retina], undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Hoefler Type Foundry, Inc.
    - [Every Art Director needs her own Typeface...], 1991; 1 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - [Typefaces by Hoefler Type Foundry], 1996; 1 (Box 1, Folder 40)
      Includes several loose sheets in a gray folder.
    - Presenting Muse Number 1: a specimen book of the typeface Didot, 1997; 1 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Catalogue of Typeface, fourth-seventh editions., 2000-2003; 4 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - House Industries
    - Chalet, undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Independent Project Press
    - Typefaces and ornaments, second edition, 1991; 1 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Monotype Typography Ltd.
    - The Monotype Font Index 5.0, 1995; 1 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Typotheque Type Foundry
    - Fedra Sans, 2001; 1 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - The Fedra Typeface Family, 2003; 1 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Jigsaw, 2004; 1 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - [Fedra], 2004; 2 copies (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - [Fedra, 3 sample cards: sans, mono, serif a & b], undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 50)
- Additional Material, 1971-2007
  Accession dated August 23, 2013.
  - D. Stempel AG
    - Die Schrift im Buch: Die Garamond in ihrer Verwendung im Werksatz, undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Font Bureau
    - Font Bureau Type Specimens: David Berlow, 2007; 1 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Jack Stauffacher (Greenwood Press)
    - Wooden Letters from 300 Broadway, 1999; 1 (Box 1, Folder 53)
      This item is a catalog published in conjunction with the exhibition "Jack Stauffacher, Printer," which was held at the Natalie & James Thompson Art Gallery, School of Art and Design, San Jose State University, 23 February to 26 March, 1999.
  - Tri-Arts Press, Inc.
    - Olde Type Faces at Tri-Arts Press, Inc. 331 East 38th St., New York 16, N.Y. from the Frederic Nelson Phillips Collection of Antique Exotic Ancient Type Faces Murr"ee" Hill 6-4242, 1971; 1 (Box 1, Folder 54)
- Additional Material, 1984-2008
  Various accession dates.
  - Emigre
    - Rosbeek 43 / Emigre., 1998; 1 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Entschedé Font Foundry
    - Lexicon, 1997; 1 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Font Bureau
    - Type specimens / Font Bureau., 1995; 1 (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - Type specimens, 3rd ed., 2001; 1 (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - One-Line type specimens, 2008; 1 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Hoefler Type Foundry
    - House & Garden, 1996; 1 (Box 4, Folder 60)
    - Presenting Muse Number 1: A Specimen Book of the Typeface Didot, 1997; 1 (Box 4, Folder 61)
    - Catalogue of Typefaces, 5th ed., 2002; 1 (Box 4, Folder 62)
    - New Typefaces, 6th ed., 2002; 1 (Box 4, Folder 63)
  - International Typeface Corporation
    - Bodoni, 1991; 1 (Box 4, Folder 64)
  - Linotype
    - ETAOINSHRDLU, Or, In Praise of Slugs..., 1984; Imprimerie dromadaire; 1 (Box 4, Folder 65)
  - Monotype
    - La typographie au plomb: un art d'imprimer, 1992; 1 (Box 4, Folder 66)
  - Schumacher-Gebler
    - 26 Letters: An Annual and Calendar by Eckehart Schumacher-Gebler & Colin Banks, eds., 1992; 1 (Box 4, Folder 67)
  - Typotheque
    - Jigsaw Herbal, undated; 1 (Box 4, Folder 68)
  - Uitgeverij de Buitenkant
    - Haagse Letters, 1996; Verheul, Peter; Lommen, Mathieu; 1 (Box 4, Folder 69)
  - Varityper
    - Type Specimen Book Addendum, undated; 1 (Box 4, Folder 70)